one of the things that disturbs me about
our cultures is how sort of unprepared
we are for tragedy in the sense like we
were in a bad spot
bad spot because because we don't have
religion I mean I you know in the way
people used to have really you know
religion not without was you know you
needed that to deal with tragedy and so
so again I guess it's education in a
time between worlds but you would almost
say religion in a time between worlds
too I wonder I wonder if you know well
there's a strong connection there I mean
and I make it in the book
pointing out basically pointing out that
if you if you take education the way I'm
taking it and not making it just about
modern schooling but mind a broader yeah
and you look at what have been the most
successful educational adventures and
organizations they the answer hands down
is the religions like as far as
facilitating intergenerational
transmission of knowledge and skill and
identity you know the religions are our
hand stand the largest most effective
educational organizations ever and it's
undeniable and I would argue in fact
that the the nature of what is discussed
in religion right the topics of ultimate
concern as Tillich would say that these
things are necessary as a part of
education that talking about death for
example yeah and it's absolutely taboo
it's like it's more taboo in in modern
education and to discuss these sorts of
things right well we separated church
and state all right so again there was
progress in that move that separate
church and state back to the 30 Years
War that was bad that was like religion
and it's worse so after that happened
you're like okay let's separate church
and state
also the fact that there's so much dead
religion around you know it's not living
religion it's just it's just the corpse
of a religion like right one and exactly
so real living religion needs to be a
part of education or else people don't
form identity well and if you don't put
real living religion and I'm saying that
and with many broad connotations I'm not
saying yeah I totally msync put prayer
and school say yeah back to Catholic you
know not at all I'm saying actually
going the opposite those could be dead
religions and that a living religion
might be something that we haven't seen
yet or a new cast of an existing
tradition but certainly not what's kind
of sold in the marketplace as religion
and that's why our identities are so odd
and why many of your students would look
to superhero movies and Star Wars and
things like that for the archetypal
ideals by which they might craft
themselves right and so the paucity of
language of self evaluation the paucity
of the language of strong evaluation and
Kosmo imaginal frameworks makes it so
that yeah there's a truncation of
identity and and that leads to a kind of
D Skilling which is this that it's it's
not just that there's an incoherence of
how we make meaning of our identity in
our life and death and tragedy it's that
that lead that becomes incapacitating at
the level of just like getting
civilization to work and that's where
that's where the trick is is that like
eventually with the mental health crisis
and other iatrogenic impacts of the kind
of basically the totalized
civilizational toxicity through put on
the individual human body we end up in a
situation where yeah we can't man can't
man the machines we can't the women
aren't teaching the kids and it's all
longer maybe you want to explain that
term iectures Genesis I I can't even say
it but hydrogenic yeah or Genesis
because I don't think many people know
this word
I don't think it's a known word and I
think it's an important word you know
that people probably should know about
absolutely yeah I mean I wish it was a
different word because it's very
difficult word iatrogenic like it's in
that's I cannot use it again right now
but it's actually a very important
concept personal to me which has to do
with harm that it's done by virtue of
being administered something like
medicine that's supposed to stop the
harm right and so after genic
technically means kind of harm done by a
doctor
medically created disease medically
created harm or injury Rossini's right
and but the pattern you can see could
apply more broadly where anytime there's
a problem you try to fix the problem and
the thing you're doing to fix the
problem is actually making the problem
worse like that you can see how that's a
general pattern so like you I argue in
my first book that likes okay the
American schools were a problem so we
used standardized testing to try to fix
that problem but standardized testing
actually made the schools worse that's
right right so that it was actually an
iatrogenic effect and Ilic makes this
argument that there's multi-level
a-after genic impacts haven't into with
basically mechanical solutions aimed at
organic problems and so medicines a
clear case but what's tricky is that you
once you've invested a lot in solving
the problem that way you're also going
to be pretty invested in not detecting
the kinds of injury and harm that you're
doing yeah by virtue of trying to fix
the problem and so that means that a
hydrogenic effects are hard to detect
and so when Ilic wrote about this in
medicine and the seven is he was already
seeing things that have now mushroomed
almost out of control and i believe we
are looking at something like an
iatrogenic plague where a very large
percentage of the populations of the
industrial west will be pretty severely
disabled in the coming decade not by
virtue of addiction
not by virtue of pandemic but by virtue
of basically following the dictates of
the existing masturbation's of the
medical industry it's interesting like
we were talking on the intellectual dark
web
you know forum about Jordan Peterson and
people were saying oh he's he's you know
good or bad or they're having this
discussion and you and you came in and
said you know the thing that's going on
with him right now is that this actual
Genesis no curse mistake that and and
that's like his his his his massive fame
and then and then and then suddenly sort
of this this this tragedy happening that
is a kind of archetypal kind of kind of
thing in some kind of a way I I don't
know if you know if you if you can does
that makes any sense I mean it does and
I it's unfortunate in a sense because
you know Peterson the polarization of
the polarizing nature of Peterson will
make it so that people don't actually
pay attention to the after Jenna thing
that's right in the face which is to say
if you hate Peterson then you have to
read him as an addict or try which means
that you can't see that all he was doing
was following doctor's orders and
actually that it was the drug that was
extremely dangerous right if you love
Peterson then you can't see that story
that the drug was dangerous right
because now you're actually critiquing
the whole medical system and you're
critiquing his judgment taking the drug
in the first place and you're critiquing
his prior statements about the validity
of taking psychiatric medications right
which are running on the assumption that
they don't do harm and so if you love
them you can't say the hydrogenic thing
and if you hate it we can't stay at
regenexx things are actually he's
actually got to obscure the issue
unfortunately and now I believe that an
important class of drug namely benzos
which should be understood as very
dangerous to use not because they're
addictive but because they cause certain
forms of brain damage that these will be
misunderstood as only bad because
they're addictive and or misunderstood
as only rarely rarely rarely are bad
right on the whole he made the right
choice which is the two sides of it
so I'm actually quite upset about it
because I I mean honestly have never
paid much attention to Jordan Peterson
tried and but now I have because he's
caught up in the hydrogenic plague which
I've been tracking and I'm seeing them
actually becoming a distraction from the
plague that people are caught up with
it's simulation and now I caught up in
the reality and the reality is actually
quite scary which is that it's actually
extremely common for there to be very
adverse side effects from taking
psychiatric medications as prescribed
those SSRIs and benzos
that's benzos being things like adderall
and klonopin and SSRIs things like you
know classically Prozac and now just by
saying that I can be like I know victims
of Prozac right yeah so just by saying
that I would be labeled by the American
Psychiatric Association as a
Scientologist probably and part of the
anti-psychiatry movement but in fact I'm
not I'm simply a reasonable person who's
looking at evidence and Jordan Pearson
some of the evidence if you can look
past the simulation and to the reality
of what actually happened to the man now
it's all second my friend Dave who's on
his on dialysis you know because he took
Prozac for I don't know 20 years he was
missed and and spent 20 years in bed and
you know yeah yeah I mean it's I'm sure
there's a lot of people out there like
that
yeah there are I mean it's very you said
plague that's a very strong word it
takes a strong word but it's a specific
word and again back to the thirty years
were back to that period when there was
also plagues as part of civilizational
transition which had to do with rapid
urbanization without adjustment now
and playing that actually has to do with
the side effects of the whole industrial
system and a certain approach to
handling disease from the industry
perspective and a petrochemical
perspective and so yeah there's a
there's a complexity to the plague which
means that it is arbitrarily hitting is
spreading wide is destabilizing economic
and geopolitical and we're approaching
it and it's invisible because no one
wants to talk about it and so yeah we'll
see where it goes and so so by your what
you're describing is people being taking
drugs for psychiatric illnesses take
taking bad drugs for it is that what
you're describing because you are much
more than that I'm describing basically
the the entire industrial complex of
late capitalist medical system
disgusting okay so I'm describing a
system that has young children on
multiple drugs at unprecedented rates
and old people over 60 so-called poly
drugged at unprecedented rates none of
which has been studied negative effects
already being documented it's um it's
like a massive experiment on the whole
population like I study ADHD medication
situation very carefully and so I can
speak to that other people can speak to
some of the other issues but yeah it's
it's a massive experiment on the human
nervous system and you say something
about ADHD can you say something about
that that's I mean we're back to the
dyslexia that right so we are looking at
a typical nervous systems like we're
looking at kids each kid having a
different nervous system that's the max
each kid actually has a profoundly
unique nervous system thank God and so
when you're in a situation where the
unique nervous system doesn't
necessarily fit well in the standard
container then you either need to blame
the container or blame the nervous
system right so a lot of what's
happening with the ADHD kind of crisis
and if you look at the numbers of the
kind of escalating diagnosis and the
diagnostic creep and numbers of
prescriptions it's a large large number
of kids over a short period of time and
the numbers are actually my book I'd
document the actual numbers and the
billion the billions being made by
companies selling ritalin
direct-to-consumer have that as part of
that due to the united states and but
what you're looking at is a tendency to
want to avert attention from critique of
the forms of schooling and put attention
on the biological substrate of the
individual right which is to say that if
school is not working for you right is
it because you have a disease like
problem with your brain that's probably
genetic you know right which is at the
end of the day the story about ADHD is
turning into some story about
genetically ingrained differences in
neurological maturation which kind of
make it so the prefrontal cortex in
other parts of the central control
system come on to kids at different
times and in different contexts in
different ways right that's what the
story is
in some extreme states of exposure to
toxic chemicals and other things you can
get severely dysregulated states where
but that's oh we're talking like that's
a very rare compared to what we're
looking at in schools today where we're
getting the prescriptions and so that
the arguments something like you know
unless we changed schooling and start to
think radically differently about it
like in a concrete utopian way like my
educational hub network vision or
actually getting kids out of these
intolerable situations and
duplicitous situations in
self-contradictory and meaningless and
nonsensical situations which is what
school often feels like yeah we need to
get them out of there because if we
don't then we're just gonna ad DS just
gonna keep increasing and depression
will keep increasing there we give them
away and a TD mats and the Stars and
then they'll have reactions both of
those suicides right and so it ends up
being yeah the the the kind of you know
the externalities of the system are
being displaced into the bodies of the
youth and when I talk about a
catastrophic bifurcation of
intergenerational transmission being a
kind of a vector of civilizational
collapse those oh yeah it ends up well
you know yeah you know and it's a kind
of generational warfare action
generational warfare I mean look at the
debt look at the debt and then now look
at the iatrogenic burden being placed on
the youth like what are we gonna expect
them to do and what are we gonna expect
them to think of us for leaving them in
this situation and so yeah so that feels
to me like rough the plague is here
basically is what you're saying the
plague is here I'm saying something like
the plague is approaching and we've and
we are the cause and therefore the cause
is unspeakable and as a Rastafari none
you said he said look how Babylon works
the school's make you stupid the money
makes you pour the medicine makes you
sick yeah right and so this is it the
system has reached a point where now it
is turning into its opposite right the
system has grown to a point where now
its internal contradictions are
beginning to dissolve it but maybe
that's the good news is it's sort of
reached a level of toxicity that's
becoming transparent like you can see it
I hope so but before you it was harder
see well it's getting harder to see
because we're compromising our nervous
systems as a result of a I'd reject
playing right so this is the one of the
main problems you have with certain
forms of our Genesis is that they affect
the nervous system precisely in such a
way that you can't recognize that your
conference the people on the Senate
floor I think think they're thinking
clearly like I don't think they know
that they're well they're in the matrix
so correct
do you expect them to do but but you
know programmed so you know in the kind
of in the fog of the time between worlds
yeah it's dicey right down to the level
of the biological substrate and yeah so
we'll we'll see but yes so the at row
genic term is very important and you
know hopefully another person or group
will somehow very attention to the issue
that is known as polarizing peterson so
people can actually look through the
simulation of the reality and hopefully
around so that's the one narrative you
will see in the culture about problems
with the medical industry you will see
the addiction and exactly a very
interesting narrative because it ends up
in a sense placing responsibility on the
individual who is actually on the
receiving end of the system right most
of the so-called addicts even on opiates
were placed on them as part of surgical
procedure or some other normal thing and
what you're looking at is actually
something like physical dependency which
is different than the patient and so
that's another thing that's running
interference between culture actually
seeing that regenexx addiction
mm-hmm of course very dangerous to even
talk about this stuff this one is used
when you start to talk about these
things you're now you're talking about
illness you're talking about death
you're talking about fear mmm I talk
about a lot of things that actually
drive our behavior away from engaging
the truth I'm very difficult that's a
conversation I'm glad we're having it
but I don't anticipate it being
well-received that kind of ties in to
the next question that's that's coming
to me and that is I was thinking about
media and I have you know I said
initially you had this resistance to
doing a podcast and I was thinking about
that and I was thinking about how
there's all these podcasts everywhere um
and I was thinking about how odd and
strange and bizarre this even just this
kind of conversation is right you know
we've got earphones on and talking into
a microphone and and and you're in
Vermont and and I'm in like Avon France
and the whole thing is it's very strange
and I've noticed that you know I don't
know what kind of media I used to
consume but I'm listening to
conversations you know on with on
podcasts or even conversations that
aren't even at the level of podcasts
right just between people on YouTube and
it's it's very odd what's what's going
on the fuck is going on with media like
what is happening to us like on one
level I feel like I'm learning all kinds
of shit right like I'm getting a lot of
information in the rabbit hole so to
speak and on the other hand I feel
overwhelmed it does I mean I have very
different media consumption habits I
mostly read books I spend very little
time looking at the Internet
and almost no time listening to podcasts
or watching YouTube videos what's
happening is that the new point of
extraction in the global economy is now
your attention and so where it used to
be a cultural industry was relatively
benign interesting compliment to things
like steel and automobiles now it is the
case that the Society of the spectacle
runs on mining for your attention down
to the micro broadcaster and so a little
bit about what even-even Ilic was
talking about how we would move away
from from from schooling good and
opening up this sort of infinite educate
you said you're confused you said you
just know that it's weird and alienating
it could move us away from schooling and
it could be the concrete utopian dream
of the early 90s where the internet
began but it's an information ecosystem
is not an educational environment and
occasionally and an informational
ecosystem that runs on it says there's
little corners of the internet like of
course if you're a society listening to
somebody listening to this could could
could get a lot of fantastic information
right I mean and somebody who's pretty
not as educated in you as you are and
not as gifted at reading books because a
lot of people don't even read books
these are correct correct a lot of
people don't even talk to other real
people if there's a huge loneliness
epidemic so the other thing that's
happening is the screen capturing
attention moving us away from one
another and towards the images and so I
believe educational technology digital
technology networked computers could
make Gillis's vision possible but not
the way it's currently being used in my
book I lay out specific design
principles for educational technologies
that would potentially meet these
standards and they would
always move you away from the screen
towards other people so that actually
issue but even you know I think that's
sort of happening already
you know example for example a nun
meeting Alexander in Paris tomorrow and
you know he came here and we're meeting
and we we met online so so I think that
like that's like a next step right it is
and I'm not the only thing that I'm not
the only one noticing this but you have
to understand that YouTube in particular
and a lot of in Facebook in particular
and Twitter's in particular this is
about attention capture and it's about
making money off of capturing your
attention
sure period and and if we if we keep
glossing it over and saying oh but it
has the benefits and we should be on
Facebook anyway it's like no you're
misunderstanding that's like the doctor
smoking cigarettes in the 50s you don't
I'm saying like no we know that this
shit that's actually disrupting our
ability to conduct ourselves in a
civilized manner and we also notice that
we're talking and and you know this is
very interesting and something's going
on at the same time I mean I I agree
with you I you know I probably become an
addict of some kinds you know and I
probably need to wean it off it often
but okay I mean and the long-form
conversation what we're doing now is
different than asynchronous text-based
exchange right so asynchronous allow
anonymous text based exchange like
Facebook posts right yeah and Twitter
feeds oh that's not even synchronous
text-based like what like and that these
things capture the amygdala and capture
so much time and attention and as they
entrap us in that they're selling
advertisements next oh yeah so that
they're actually making money off of
their ability to capture they make the
look through asynchronous text base
exchange with a stranger who could be
here's the killer a robot and not even a
real person so it's like why do people
who have better things that could be
writing spend a ton of time writing
they're working for Facebook and working
for Twitter this is interesting to me
and again part of
we are in the simulation and how far
away we are from actually looking at
what's actually happening it's like
we're all an acid or something it's like
it's like it's like the culture has been
given us the whole culture has been
given acid but I will dead now you're
back to the at reject lake yeah you know
we have all getting back to that given a
bunch of complicated chemicals and
including the yes I'm not going together
alright yeah so now you've got me down
the rabbit hole of your critiquing the
sacred cow of social media uh-huh oh no
I mean there's there's no question in my
mind that that's terrible that's like
you know I I don't know I think probably
Facebook is the worst Facebook could be
single-handedly the worst thing down the
America I mean any cuz you could say any
extreme thing about Facebook every
terrible thing that's an interesting
point
that's how central what facebook has
captured is is that you could speculate
that as having impacts on basically
everything it's the mental health crisis
its socialization its nutrition its
health its politics it's like yeah
because it what they've done is captured
our communicative infrastructure I mean
this would have elect rolling in his
grave right it's sort of like the the
subhuman subconscious being broadcast 24
hours 7 or so we've so we keep
due to this to this that's this thing
it's not exactly where I you know I was
thinking I'm planning on going I didn't
realize that sort of you're making me
you're making me understand what a deep
issue this is this is what I didn't want
to go on podcast right because it's like
at a certain point we get past
entertainment and we get into issues
that actually make our heart go a little
bit faster and we realize that we may be
the ones in difficult situations
deciding whether to stay or to leave
right that will be thinking about the
basic needs and self regulation of our
nervous systems unexpectedly caught off
guard by doing what came natural is a
part of our civilized socialized I kind
of a bitch waited to miss and it's
already happening I look at Australia
like we go on with life as usual and but
we're in a burning house yeah well it's
not even is a very house I'm so like
sitting in the fire burning in the
tragedy like we were talking about to be
in the post tragic it's not looking away
it's actually not looking through that
makes any sense looking through this see
let me just see truth this actually look
through we look through but we and we
don't ignore the horror we don't you
know yeah yeah and the horse super close
up close and personal yeah and I can
feel inside myself as we're talking
there's a resistance to hearing this and
there's also the fact the feeling that
it's necessary right so it's like how do
we begin to talk about it like how do we
begin to talk about it like I said what
are the languages we can use so we can
all say face together and what are the
languages that we can discover that
would allow us to talk about the
unspeakable right like and I've said
this before like when when billions
watch millions die how will we handle
that what will be on the news and on
Twitter and we would behave ourselves
right or will we spiral deeper into
the performs of reactionary closed
mindedness that have driven us into the
mental health crisis in the first place
right this phrase the unbearable
intimacy of planetary catastrophe mind
closed back upon ourselves that there
are no escape hatches that every escape
hatch goes in deeper and that you're
there left with the culture and one
another yeah so you you're watching
you'll be observing the plague like how
do we react when the plague comes in a
sense yeah and also trying to find ways
to stop it you know trying to find ways
to galvanize enough kind of distributed
responsiveness capacity at the level of
the individual in the community in time
yeah
and so yeah at that point we need to go
back to your utopias I think right well
in certain innovations in civic process
like if we could find ways to return to
having conversations this is some of the
work I do with force Landry around
civilizational design and thinking about
civics work and then with Jonathan Ross
and work I do with the transformational
educational alliance right looking at
actual concrete experimental work going
on in education both in terms of what's
patching together the existing system
which is the best of the best of today
and what I call the first of the next
right which are actually truly unique
formers of Education that are responding
directly to the fact that we're in the
situation that we're in and there are
examples of those and so yes these can
you give some examples of those so you
know so we can be more a little bit more
concrete like of which of this first
kind of education that you're speaking
this knit new forms of education new new
new
forms of you know learning that you're
speaking of totally yeah I mean which
one would be useful in a chat yes oh
there's interesting stuff happening with
integrated the integration of
cryptocurrency and kind of digital
currencies with decentralized
educational networks and accreditation
right so this is the example of the work
of Madhav's Amir who was a principal in
New York City I'm thinking after reading
my book we've been constructing
basically a way to do like github for
teachers and students that ends up
allowing them to co-create curricula and
standards and then he's just wanting to
compete eventually with the existing
standardized testing infrastructures and
tie success within his system to a
digital wallet right so he's rolling out
a basic income guarantee to the next
generation on the back of an alternative
way of assessing their merit in terms of
their creativity and trying to Wed this
to the New York City kind of schooling
crisis so that the kids who are falling
between the cracks gets shuffled in and
brought up through his digital negative
accreditation system as he calls it so
that's an example of like the first of
the next where I'd you don't know his
work is it's incredible but will the
will it be exactly that I don't know but
something like that and something like
that something like that is gonna need
to emerge where we decentralized the
schools and relate the kind of like but
at this point not accredited forms of
creativity that kids are doing which are
actually going to be socially valuable
in the future find those to get
remunerate 'add through a currency
that's not necessarily the one that's
about to crash and so basically using
the educational system to reboot the
whole economic system is is where I'm
seeing that first as you said in your
book something about like a konami being
subservient to education like correct
yes
education is primary and then
then economics comes comes next after
that that's true and and that's back to
the fact that you can't even have the
economy unless you've educated the
workers and but it's also the case that
you know to what end is all of the
economic production is to for
subsistence with them beyond that we get
religion
remember religion that was all
educational all stacked on top of and
ostensibly the purpose for the economy
itself was to channel upwards into these
temples of learning and so yet there was
a camp put on and we channeled to back
up for it's God himself and for abstract
numbers and endless accumulation of
capital basically what we could have
been channeling it up and into basically
an infinite educational game and so if
you place an infinite educational game
on the top of what we know as now the
kind of economy then you end up getting
something that runs a little bit
differently yeah so the educational hub
network which I proposed in the book is
actually something like that it's as you
mentioned the first sentence getting
going something like the infinite
frontier of human potential that we
don't have an infinite frontier of
resources on the planet and I guess we
can start mining asteroids but there is
a way in which we do have an infinite
frontier of human potential that's
already here and so switching kind of
like commodity frontiers from the actual
material resources to these resources
within the human is already underway I
remember there capturing your attention
so it was about actually leveraging the
move into new aspheric extraction and
actually transforming and actually
transforming that into a net benefit by
turning it into an education centric
society and that was kind of a mouthful
but that's in a sense division and when
you think about you know what could be
the thing that a civilization could be
about in order to exist in perpetuity it
would need to be about finding ways
to educate humans within the
civilization order then make that
civilization better right this is the
conveniences vision that the
civilization needs to teach all things
to all people that the civilization is
fundamentally that's what civilizing
means it means to be educating in such a
way that it can reproduce itself and
grow itself in an all-men's of the
educational function of the civilization
is the autopoietic function of the
social critic you write that the
educational function is the self
maintaining and the self transforming of
the civilization which means that you
need to make it in the sense to focus
you can't have the education be about
the civilization building capital you
can't have the education be about the
civilization creating Wars you have to
have the education be about the
civilization being educational and then
you're into the infinite frontier of
human potential and the temple of
learning stacked on top of the economics
boy that's important that's like that's
that's just that's so important I mean
it's just like it's just a total
reorientation of you know how people are
think of themselves as human beings but
basically that's what you're this you
know just that's one of our difficulties
is that we're gonna have to reimagine
ourselves beyond the category of wage
labor for example yeah going to school
and getting a job and all that crap is
like right that's not really what it's
about
yeah Wow yeah
that blows me away and actually III
think that the fact that you propose an
idea like that it almost may
it almost makes it possible when such an
idea is being proposed does that make
sense it could be I mean you have to
imagine it I don't know what I'm trying
to say here I'm trying to say that yeah
it has to be imagined first has to be
imagined first of course you know it's
there's also the concrete utopian
theorist is also always accused it and I
have at a right right well I mean you
get me excited when you're talking about
this good and then I stop myself when I
think hmm am I being naive here right
exactly the naivete and then also the
sense that of too much of a generalist
that you're moving across too many
fields and that you're seeing the force
but not the trees and and so I think
this is true but at the same time I
think that you know there's no escape
from having some kind of articulate
vision yeah like we need to have some
language about the future you know and
the other thing I mean that's the social
vision there's also a Cosmo vision there
has Moe imagined all vision that is part
of that new educational system because
remember as we discussed if you don't
have real living religion within the
educational system it's weird so so
there's another piece to the
reconstruction to get to the other world
on the other the that reconstructing
that involves rebuilding kind of Cosmo
vision I'd not so this is the work I do
with Gaffney in a Cosimo neurotic
humanism right dandy needs to be a new
fundamental kind of way to craft
narratives not a new single narrative
but a new language that's available so
people can begin to construct narratives
together and opening the possibility for
new kind of Cosmo imaginal visions I
like that word but it really just means
that your story of everything like what
is your ultimate environment yeah and so
I was listening to an Orthodox Jewish
person talk about the Messiah and he was
just saying you know I got really caught
up in what he was saying and it sounded
so true it's like okay if you're if
you're an orthodox
Jew you would you would say the Messiah
you know it's not that you you want to
have faith in the Messiah he will come
it's just like it's absolutely has to
come and it is it's almost like and I
was like getting into this and I'm not
an orthodox you at all but but but I was
thinking about about you know even you
could we get the darker we talk about
all these things like the plague and and
the extreme darkness at the same time as
we're talking about this something else
emerges you know it's like the two
things arise simultaneously you could
call it Messiah if you wanted or the the
principle that's going to that's going
to save civilization all right and
there's a saying in the Kabbalah
something like greater is the darkness
that comes from the light yeah and this
was actually like one of these Talmudic
like you know double marginalia on a
phrase from the Bible which is something
like greater is the darkness than the
light but sound like well great is the
darkness and the light that's obvious
that's not why would you even write that
graters the darkness doesn't seem so
then you reinterpreted graters is the
darkness that comes from light which
deepens it and it ends up being what
you're talking about which is then yes
precisely in the darkness that and then
the broke and the broken shards that the
lights gonna begin to shine through and
so that's why it's gonna be important as
the things begin to break in that we
that love becomes primary known again
and so we don't become you know sort of
ensnared and and and and in endless
dystopian visions of you know and
unrealistic you know one that we don't
turn away from each other and that we
know what to do with the stranger you
know back to the Jewish tradition like
the Old Testament is about the stranger
what do you do with the stranger so
Gaffney scholarship shows that the word
stranger occurs in the text almost more
than any other and so you're looking at
this complication around
what do we do we meet the stranger on
the road right in between civilizations
in between law right in between rock and
story what do we do with the stranger on
the road yeah you know how do we not
turn away and you know yeah
so that's some of some of the other
facets of the vision I have to do with
getting that language rebuilt that would
allow us to have good reason and social
sanction to deal with the strange on the
road yeah no civilized way yeah I love
the stranger how to love the stranger
exactly I love the stranger yeah how do
you love the stranger and according to
most of our kind of social science you
don't you can't you built your built not
to whereas now there needs to be a
different niche as possible but it
requires these more robust languages and
requires probably it seems to me that
like religion is coming back it is like
it's like it's the opposite of what you
would think if you are like a Marxist or
something it's like we're get it or
we're gonna become more and more just
free of religion and more rational and
more yeah but it seems like it seems
like religion is just gonna come back
like like it for better and purer better
exactly for better and for worse there
could be and more crazy cults but also a
more nor like you know and explicitly
and implicitly so there'll be a lot of
things which are held with religious
fervor
which are not technically religious but
that's a religious thing happening right
there and as this situation heats up
yeah the religiosity is going to
intensify and so there will be new
religions definitely and there will be a
return to religion and to the religious
pathos and ethos yeah even in things
that are not technically religious so
that that's is the some of the feeling
we're having
turn to extremism has to do with that
I think tendency of the human psyche to
find a way to to give something ultimate
meaning mmm very interesting yeah so
actually this kind of fanaticism you
know if you if you look at it as the
shadow of something that that you know
as you say that the ultimate that could
be the of the ultimate meaning or yes I
strange times the strangeness of what's
hitting me in this conversation is just
it's just the strangeness of the times
that we're living in and what kind of
religion do we need I think we spoke to
it right yeah I think we need one that
allows us to to love the stranger and
you know and to to I think provide non
reciprocated care all right so we need
to find a religion that can get us out
of transactional zero-sum gaming and
into giving without thought or receiving
that there needs to be profound
generosity and compassion instilled in
the human heart and that's part of what
allows us to love the stranger the basic
thing you know yeah and so so yeah in a
sense I would like to see you know and
it's funny because I in my experience a
lot of the religion that we're currently
saying has to do with state experience
and kind of like in a sense the
cultivation of personal meaning and the
end the kind of like deepening of
intensity of impersonal meaningfulness
which is important and so we're sitting
and meditating and trying to attain
Satori or something high
that's actually we're doing we're doing
drugs right or doing psychedelics having
all these incredible sort of experiences
well there's something that's and so
maybe the ethical part of that the
ethical part of that and and again
having idle part of that do those things
help you love the stranger and will
those things allow you to give non
reciprocated care and concern to people
and so that's just the question that
needs to be asked and so I think yet
there's an element of explicit emphasis
on service and charity that one finds in
some of the judeo-christian traditions
which could give a shit if you can
meditate and what your state experiences
are and how many plant journeys you've
been on yeah that's why the sort of the
East and the West have to kind of meet
they do they do we knew we needed all of
the yoga's from the east right we need
we do because otherwise it's too hard to
give otherwise it's too hard to give and
you don't we need to be able to
integrate we need to have wisdom right
we need to but we also need to have
history and the categories of the
stranger which don't exists once you're
up and out and Satori and and and so
that's what's interesting too is that as
history heats up the history those
religions a deal with historicity become
important but those religions that say
that there is no history become
attractive and that's one of the
situations were anywhere that you can
see in a sense some of the religions as
a way out because that is that is that
the New Age is that what you're talking
about when you say that the religion
that is in all this talk about being in
the now and that sort of thing it's like
some of the New Age stuff you know it's
kind of like just it's experiencing at
the moment and you know and becoming
mindful when you eat your food and so
what it's like give me something a
little bit deeper than that please all
right right and something with content
of moral and ethical instruction
and of sustenance for the soul and
tragedy there's a difference between
getting that unbearable image out of
your mind
and getting the unbearable image out of
your mind and getting them bare and then
that's out of your mind
then holding the unbearable image and
finding ways to discuss with others and
so again I like that at all that that's
that seems to me that that seems to be
like so holding the unbearable image
that's the phantom and again that's from
the alchemical tradition and has to do
with a process of purification kind of
darkening blackening when you're going
down and down and in as opposed to up
and out down in him down and into
history down and into uniqueness down
into situation ala day and that is so
the religions that allow us to
characterize those intimate spaces and
to place the heroic within the personal
as opposed to the heroic and the
transpersonal or the heroic in the
public we placed the heroic in the in
the personal sphere and in what he was
intimate in what's most intimate and the
work that's done right here between
people in actual conversation and that
again as things unfold and heat up
there's this question of can we stay
with one another and not turn away from
each other now generally from the
stranger and then feel the reality of
love this is again like that it's real
and that it is not part of the
simulation and this happens of course
when there's natural disasters and it's
always kind of commented upon like the
way like after 9/11 for example the
number of people who were spontaneously
talking to one another trying to take
care of one another looking after one
another in the immediate
who on any other given day would have
just walked by one another not even
maybe there's a tricky to do that in an
ordinary day when you're just going
through your ordinary day right it is
but it's also that we're not subject to
tragedy right now as we're speaking you
know right and we are sort of leaning
into into that a little bit like that
where whereas if there was some tragedy
yes well you know our hearts would would
explode open and you know we didn't
breathe you know we would want to do
something in and but but in its it may
be in the most banal States that's when
it's it's but that's what I'm saying is
that where does the doctor you know
there's no like day to day or every day
right now in those parts of Australia
like there's not like a daily routine
that people are stuck in like I'm sure
they're trying to find it and get in it
yeah though again we're back to out of
the simulation into the reality of the
fact that a lot of people in the West
are gonna have their day-to-day routines
completely disrupted in the coming
decade and and and so that's this issue
of what how will we respond and do we
have the cultural resources to respond
in the civilized way and back to the
educational and a hydrogenic crisis so
yeah but there's a there's a there's an
intensity to to the focus that's needed
on the part of I think educators and
artists and people of that ilk because
it's gonna be on them who it falls to
create the contexts and languages
symbols by which we start to make sense
of this and I'm trying to draw more and
more people up to that level of creative
endeavor and need because what's
existing out and the culture is just not
enough for people to be able to make
sense of what's happening in their lives
no there's nothing there right so they
look for more and more and more and more
and more so they get many many many
hours of content but never actually the
thing that's gonna get them something
that would allow them to step away
from a Content and solve a problem and
so yeah there's a shitload of work to do
and so many unique individual gifts to
be given all that to be galvanized yeah
yeah I again had this sort of this thing
of the apocalypse right I keep thinking
of all these biblical things to them but
the apocalypse red isn't it mean
something like the revealing what's
what's there what's what's it does what
do you do when when this happens when
the apocalypse come is like that's like
you know if we're if we're in this sort
of place like what do you do it at that
point and that's that's the the whole
issue right right totally totally I mean
that's why often I'm like I'm not super
interested in saving the world but I'm
super interested in saving souls right
but when you are thinking opposed be a
soul is more important than the world
though yeah that's what I'm saying so
think about hospice care like we're in a
situation of civilizational hospice care
again even if something new emerges this
one's still dying so we're in a
situation of needing to allow something
to die and actually hopefully finding a
way to save the soul of the thing that's
dying and not like I'm not trying to get
into ontology or anything yeah trying to
get into the way that you can relate to
something that needs to pass but still
needs to be cared for and that needs to
actually be brought to a kind of view
beautification it's brought to a kind of
self clarity right so if you think of
Erikson Erik Erikson's developmental
model his final stage of adult
maturation involved this crisis between
integrity and despair and it had to do
with how can you make sense of your life
in the face of death right and you
either despair that you can't make sense
of that it was all just senseless or you
find a way to integrity' Slee I didn't
integrity hold the meaning of your life
and so this is what you do when you face
the apocalypse that happens in every
moment also it's like it can or you can
feel a sense of despair in every moment
and you can also find this
openings but at the same time it is
possible to get to ericksonian integrity
without actually confronting death if
you're able to be aware and against burn
in the tragedy of all of life which is
saturated with death and see the
transience so this is where you know
again you can't throw the meditative
traditions out because they bring
certain things in which is the ability
to look carefully an experience and yeah
so I my sense is that the state of
Apocalypse is one where precisely that
you and face the integrity versus
despair and integrity doesn't mean
fixing it integrity it means living it
grappling with it making meaning and
basically again the beautification and
the self clarification that can only
happen as some things come to an end
it's very interesting that you you you
bring the word beautification together
with with death yeah totally there's
something about about beautification and
death that those two things I don't know
how to articulate that but yeah I mean
you know the what would a civilization
be like in which everyone had a
beautiful death like that's an
interesting question how far are we from
this image you know Wow yeah and it's
Ilic too and this is one image
responders village about medical nemesis
like that death itself is commodified
process the death itself that were taken
from us is the dignity to die in the way
that we choose to do it's yeah that's
why you can use religious language here
and talk about sin and things like that
because it really is you know what could
be more of a sin than that is stealing
away somebody's death you know or or
you're also taking their the whole you
know for Tillich it was sometime you
know putting infinite Worth and
importance in something that's not
infinite right and so that the
displacement again back to the purser
news ever watch it really religiosity
about things that aren't actually
religion right like you hold this belief
about this thing X with as much fervor
and religiosity as you would have as if
it was a religious idea and it's because
you've invested it with infinite Worth
even though it's not infinite
and so that's idolatry which is a form
of sin which was plaguing the simulation
right now because we're loading a bunch
of incredibly superficial transient
things with profound and almost infinite
worth not realizing that actually it's
not going to be there very soon and or
by the way it's a scientific finding in
scientific findings change that's what
scientific findings do that's how
science works so if you invested all in
that that means we can't have science
grow and learn because this way viewing
the reality of science has become idle
oh yeah well it's become it's it's
science is infused with religiosity so
it's correct in our to the blue church
to the blue churches who would string me
up for what I said about the iatrogenic
plague and psychiatric medications
because they would assume that I'm an
auntie back sir which might as well make
me a Holocaust denier and so there's a
there's an intensity of commitment it's
not even I come in with anything it's
just an ideology which you've been
Harrigan it's like you haven't even
thought about it it's like usually
usually yeah are you just you're just
you're just regurgitating things he's
something you saw on Facebook good I
hope we're not complaining too much here
all right yeah that's the thing I wonder
who's gonna even get to this point and
be like these cynical bastards just
because we've also we've talked about
death and beautification right those
things have been like that that's the
essence of this conversation right go
ahead things were happening at the same
time exactly so I think that's it Zak I
think I think it was right we've I think
that's where we've landed that's right
death and beautification yeah beautiful
death well thank you very much I think
that's right this conversation has
exceeded all of my expectations of what
the limited that was great